And this is a shorter video lecture introducing my class on City and Climate Action.
Or this is really kind of an exploration or maybe a rationale perhaps, but why you should
take this class, MIT 11.165 for undergraduates or 11.477 for graduate students.
This video lecture, really, I'm going to use this as an example of all the future video
lectures that are to come.
So for example, I'm not going to go over this slide.
This slide has all the readings that are in the syllabus for today.
I'll generally start my lectures with a slide like this, but I won't go into it because
first, all these things are on the syllabus.
Second, for all the students taking this class at MIT, you'll have the PDF slides available
on the Canvas site.
So you can go to the PDF slides and click on the links.
You don't need to go click on the links for the ones on the syllabus because you already
have the syllabus.
But if I bring in other reports or articles or sources or papers, I'll put those references
into the slides.
And so if you want to follow up on other topics, just go to the slide and click on the link
in the PDF.
So while we watch the short video today, I'm going to use the short video class to comment
on or synthesize, but not recap the readings.
So you do have to do the readings for the point of watching the video lectures to really
set up our discussion or to demonstrate something I want to highlight or explore.
Quite often, my lectures, I really like doing a deep dive in a particular aspect of the
readings, but that might not be necessarily what we want to talk about together in class.
So I'll highlight things or explore things that I want to focus on.
We can discuss it more in class.
And then for the student leaders of the discussions, you can highlight something you want to explore
or highlight and we can talk about it in class.
What I'm hoping this is going to allow us to do is to allow you to watch or rewatch these
videos on your own time or at your own pace.
And hopefully what it's going to allow us to do is to flip the classroom and enable us
to have richer, longer discussion.
We have about three hours of class time together, given the number of people in the room today.
I'm hoping we can use all three hours so everyone can feel like they're getting something out
of the discussions.
The fun thing is that sometimes those discussions go to different places than we expect or that
I expect.
And ultimately, the reason why I'm making these short videos is that these videos are going
to form the basis of a new digital course on cities and climate action.
Ultimately, I hope to make these videos available to faculty or students at other departments
at other schools.
I would argue that actually as urban planners, we need to get involved in climate change,
but also at the same time, we may not have the faculty or staff or student bandwidth to
take a new course or offer new class.
So I'm hoping these video courses will enable people to do that.
At the same time, I think that a lot of other disciplines like engineering and policy could
benefit from focusing on cities because cities I'll argue to in this next few slides are
a key scale or jurisdiction at which we can have a lot of opportunities to take climate
action.
So one reading I just want to focus on just to demonstrate how I'm going to delve deeper
into certain readings.
I want to introduce the textbook for this class.
It's a book by David Mackay.
He was a British physicist.
I think he was a royal astronomer or a royal physicist at some point in the UK.
He wrote this book in 2009.
And unfortunately, he passed away to relatively young age in 2016.
But this book is actually a fairly good legacy.
It was wildly popular then.
It's still fairly popular now, even 13 or 14 years later.
And it's popular for a lot of reasons.
It's accessible.
David Mackay made this book free, actually.
He put as a PDF on the web.
It's actually a fairly funny.
A lot of the students find this book quite entertaining.
The evaluations for the course always highlight this textbook.
Students really enjoy reading this textbook, so I hope you do too.
It actually uses a fairly simple but powerful back of the envelope reasoning.
David Mackay almost always starts with fairly basic physical principles, looks at empirical
data and uses simple reasoning or calculations or graphics to enable people to understand
the key issues involved.
I have to say, in the first chapter, David Mackay makes the point that there's no economics
in this book.
And we can talk about whether or not that's good or bad.
One thing that has wildly changed since 2009 is the cost of renewable energies and technologies,
our renewable energy technologies have all declined since 2009.
This book has become a huge advantage for renewable energy over fossil fuel energies.
And that's why the energy transition is going to happen more and more rapidly in our lifetimes.
So we can discuss whether or not it's good or bad this textbook has no economics.
It simply focuses on the technological issues involved, rather than the economic issues.
Similarly, it really doesn't focus on the political or policy aspects of some of these
technologies.
This is perhaps before, well, climate change has always been fairly polarized in the U.S.
in a way that's not polarized in other countries.
But David Mackay makes an effort in this book, basically not to focus on politics as much
as on the physical or technological solutions we need.
He assumes that that will help drive the conversation or help drive the policy changes needed.
Obviously, we haven't had the policy changes we needed in the U.S.
And Europe is slightly ahead, but perhaps does not move as quickly as we'd like it to
also.
Discuss in this class, but now we think the lack of emphasis on politics and policy is
also appropriate.
But let me show you some of the strengths of the book, and I'll use one example I really
like.
Let me, before I do that, I'll just show you that because it's accessible, because you
made the PDF free, and download the PDF for free on the website, shows you where to buy
it in paper.
But this is actually a volunteer thing that somebody read the book likes enough because
the content was free, made a separate webpage for every single chapter.
So you can access this book through the PDF on download.
You can buy a hard copy, I'll show you a hard copy in class today, or you can simply look
at the web pages, or you can do some combination all through to access the book.
That's why it's quite accessible.
And it's been translated into, it looks like, 10 or 12 other languages.
To show you one aspect of the book I really like, I like the use of graphics in all of
David Mackay's work.
You can see the very simple graph on the vertical axis is carbon dioxide concentration in the
atmosphere.
On the horizontal axis is time going all the way back to like about 1000 AD.
He focuses on this little section, which is between 1600 and 2000, and this puckish commentary
in the caption here is, I think something new may have happened between 1800 and 2000
AD.
He marks the year 1769, which is when James Watt added the steam engine.
That's the beginning of the Industrial Revolution in the UK.
And you can say, you can see in the UK and countries like France, Germany and the US,
the Industrial Revolution begins, and carbon dioxide concentrations go straight up exponentially.
If you look at this graph as long as 2000, I think in 2020, we're about 415 or 420 parts
per million in the atmosphere.
So we've fully exceeded this growth has continued unabated the last 22 years.
But if you look at how he examines the issues, what I really like in all of his work and
this text book is that he uses graphics to kind of illustrate different issues.
For example, he takes World Greenhouse Gap Missions in his numbers from 2000, about 34
gigatons of CO2 equivalent per year.
Basically says that's the total area of greenhouse gas missions.
And if you compare that to the population of 2006 billion people, of course, seven
point something now or almost eight billion people on the planet, that basically averages
to about five tons of CO2 equivalent per year person.
So you multiply this axis and this axis and you get the results resulting area of 34 gigatons
of CO2 equivalent per year.
But, you know, we can also look at some of the numbers and they've been updated our world
and data is a pretty useful website for looking at different sources of data.
These are slightly different definition of annual CO2 emissions.
They exclude land use change.
And so in 2000, they have about 25 billion tons of CO2 equivalent.
What you can see what happens is basically it has gone straight up over the last 22
years, still this slight dip in COVID.
So if you look at their definition and data is 25 billion tons in 2000, 30, almost
37 billion tons in 2019 until slightly declines of COVID.
And what we're hoping after COVID is that as our energy transition continues, we aren't
bouncing up back to the same upper trajectory, which is going to result in more climate change.
At the same time, you can use the original graphics.
You can kind of drill down into the data a little bit as David Mackay does.
And shows that these areas of greenhouse gas emissions are quite different.
Even though the total area of greenhouse gas emissions is what counts, if you average
over, let's say, different populations of people in different regions, you can see
that, you know, even if the total area of Asia might be slightly larger North America,
there's many fewer people in North America who are meeting much more greenhouse gas
emissions per person.
And this is starting to highlight some issues perhaps of equity across different regions
of the world.
If you look at by a country, most of the people in North America are Americans who
are all in 2000, looks like meeting about 24 tons per person per year, even though
China has a larger population of nearly a billion people, those people on average
only have four tons per person per year.
So in 2000, by this measure, it looks like the average American is emitting on six
times the average Chinese person.
Having said that, the average Chinese person is still emitting twice as much as the
average Indian person here.
And so the area of greenhouse gas emissions from India is consequently roughly less
than half of what it is from China.
If we were to update this for 2019, you can see that's changed in this graphic.
China has become clearly the largest greenhouse emitter in the world.
The area is even emitting twice as much as the average Chinese person.
You can also see some changes over time.
You can see that the US is now emitting, it looks like around 15 tons per person
per year.
They might be slightly different measures, but greenhouse gas emissions have
declined in the US.
They've gone up in China and now China is above the world average of about 4.4
tons per year per capita.
And if you look at India, India is still well below average.
Sub-Saharan Africa is even smaller.
And so what we're trying to do is look at how this might translate into national
policy, or at least what we think the responsibility of different countries
are to deal with climate change.
If you look at historical greenhouse gas emissions, if you average all the
greenhouse gas emissions over the last 120 years, you see the United States is
clearly responsible for the largest area of greenhouse gas emissions per person
per year over that time period.
If you look at a total historical or cumulative greenhouse gas emissions,
again, the US clearly, unfortunately, number one here, double that of China.
And it looks like triple that of Russia.
Having said that, this will change over time as annual emissions change.
But what we're basically seeing here is the US has the largest responsibility
for total historical greenhouse gas emissions over the last 170 years.
And what are we doing in this kind of reading?
I'm only digging down into this particular issue because I want to
highlight what I want to try to do in this class, which is first develop
your basic numerical literacy.
In this case, we're looking at greenhouse gas emissions per capita over time.
I want to understand broad issues like equity or climate action, which countries
are responsible for climate action by taking specific deep dives.
So we looked a little bit at different data sources, a different trend over time
or different ways to analyze the data.
And, you know, ultimately, what we're trying to do is build a moral case for
climate action. I take a US focus in this class because the US is the largest
historical emitter of greenhouse gas emissions and still on a per capita basis,
one of the highest emissions in many countries in the world.
So I would argue that actually leads to a moral case or moral responsibility
for us to take more climate action than other countries.
If you look at companies like India or regions like Sub-Saharan Africa,
they are well below the global average for them to develop or to even achieve
a standard living like our own.
They really have nowhere to go but up in terms of their gas gas emissions.
Honestly, if you want to achieve decarbonization, the US and other rich
countries have nowhere to go but down.
And that is the crux of our energy transition challenge going forward.
And so let's talk about why we focus on cities.
A quite often MIT.
This is a courtesy of my terrible, terrible PowerPoint skills.
But if you what we talk about MIT quite often is technology, policy and markets.
We talk about developing new technologies through our science and engineering
and research. We talk about trying to pass new policies through advocacy
or also based on our social science research.
And we often talk about developing new markets for technologies
through, let's say, commercialization or innovation or creating new technologies.
But I would argue to you that cities have a role at the intersection of all these.
And as a scale, is this is a underappreciated scale or an opportunity
for us to try to affect all three of these areas.
We know that technologies can be developed for certain situations
or certain combinations of problems.
Different cities are going to have different adaptation
and mitigation needs that need to be met by technology.
Cities are large enough to pass their own policies that can help shape
the adoption of technology and how the markets develop in that particular region.
And cities are large enough themselves to constitute a market for new technologies.
Cities are responsible for most of the GDP in the world.
And so we have the ability at the local level to shape technology and policy also.
So the intersection of technology, policy, markets and Venn diagram.
I'd argue to cities are a key venue for climate action.
If another reason, quite simply, why we should look at cities
is that's where all the people are.
This is the graph of the percentage of urban world population
as a proportion of the total population of the UN World Urbanization prospects.
You can see then every region in the world,
if the blue is the world population and red is the urban population,
every region of the world, Africa, Asia and Europe.
Europe is already quite urbanized at 75 percent now,
but it will become even more urbanized by 2050,
which is our mid-century argument for decarbonization.
Asia is right at 50 percent, half and half between urban world population,
but will become even more urban over the next 20 years.
That'll be mostly urbanization happening in Southeast Asia or India.
And Africa is 42 percent urbanized, but by 2050, it's going to be about 60 percent urbanized.
That's mostly urbanization that's going to occur in Sub-Saharan Africa.
If you look at Latin America and Caribbean already amazingly urbanized
at 81 percent, North America at 82 percent,
but both regions will be probably pushing 85 or 90 percent urbanized by 2050.
And Oceania, which is Australian New Zealand
and the Pacific Islands will probably stay roughly as urbanized as it is,
which is already 68 percent.
So the argument for focusing on cities is simply that's where all the people are.
That's where all the economic activity is.
That's what we should focus on to try to reduce our consumption.
We're going to focus on U.S. cities in this class,
partly simply because we're teaching in an American institution.
Also, we've had recent climate developments, which are quite exciting to me.
Here's an article by Marion Wasser at WBOR,
just simply saying what we need to know about the new Massachusetts Climate Law
that's going to affect our state energy policy quite a bit.
This is a blog post from Amy Turner at Columbia University
focusing on how cities will be affected by the Inflation Reduction Act,
which is our first major piece of climate legislation ever passed by climate
and by Congress ever since Congress learned about climate change
and the problem the first time 30 years ago.
And so I welcome insights and comparisons with other countries.
I've done work in a number of other countries on energy and energy transition,
but we're going to focus mostly in the past on U.S. cities
simply because we have the moral responsibility to take climate action
and also because they're studying in a U.S. institution.
But again, I welcome your insights and comparisons with other countries.
I'll try to bring in comparisons with other places I've worked or other regions
as appropriate to try to illustrate some of these energy and climate issues
and how they work in other cities around the world.
And I also want to highlight that there's nothing in this class really should be off limits.
And I just want to emphasize that different people will get different value
from different readings.
For some people, Bill Gates was a ruthless monopolist in the 90s,
a successful philanthropist in the aughts and the, let's say, early teens of the century.
And you might have heard most recently, he had a terrible, terrible divorce
and maybe his reputation somewhat damaged by that.
But he's also known as somebody who's worked on child mortality
and disease and climate change and pandemics.
So you wrote an article in 2018 about climate change in the 75 percent problem
arguing that we need new technologies and innovation to solve large parts
of climate change that we don't already know how to solve.
At the same time, we have this article by Nicola Jefferson and Leah Stokes,
who are our graduates from DUSH and MIT, and this title
are racist fossil fuel energy system.
And I actually think it gives a number of good arguments
why the fossil fuel energy system disproportionately affects black Americans.
This is an article that was written in July 2020,
right at the height of the Black Lives Matter protests.
And it highlighted basically how the energy system affects
different groups, especially black Americans, differently.
Having said that, people have very different reactions.
This is one student who came from the fossil fuel industry
and she was quite offended by this article that she called
our racist fossil fuel industry, which wasn't actually the title of the article,
which just shows you how this label of labeling the energy system as racist.
She took quite personally.
And so I want to emphasize that you could look at both these articles
by Bill Gates or Jefferson Stokes, and you can have different reactions to them.
But what I want us to do is try to read lots of different viewpoints
and engage with them and think through what we agree with or we don't agree with
and use that to shape our viewpoints.
And this is just to emphasize that the point of your education
is to develop your own critically-reasoned viewpoint.
But to develop your own critically-reasoned viewpoint,
you have to engage with evidence to engage with other people's viewpoints
and you have to engage with other people.
So we're going to try to have nothing to be off limits in this class,
even as we try to engage things rationally and respectfully,
respectful of other people's viewpoints.
I want us to try to keep on working and on developing our own critical reasoning
and trying to contrast and compare how other people see some of the same issues,
even if we don't agree with them.
And so in our class, I want to emphasize that we're going to learn question
and reason together.
Finally, I wrote this article this summer with a number of colleagues
around the planning discipline, including Chris Egers, who's here at MIT.
The article is titled,
Planning the Built Environment and Land Use Towards Deep Decarbonization of the United States.
And I wrote this article with my colleagues because we argue that,
you know, deep decarbonization is basically our net zero goal for 2050.
At the same time, we don't think that there's wide understanding
of what we need to do with the built environment land use.
And this is to say two things that the built environment land use
are going to be critical to realizing our energy transition goals.
And the same time, if we don't address the built environment and land use,
we may not reach those goals.
And we think that decarbonization has implications for cities
and planning in terms of the scale of how we plan cities.
The scope of what planners look at.
The speed with which planning occurs.
We need to achieve a decarbonization goal,
which is basically changing our entire energy system 28 years from now.
That's going to require planners to operate much faster.
And we need to make sure that we remain relevant.
If planners don't focus on mitigating greenhouse gas emissions,
we will be left out of larger climate discussions
happening in other disciplines or in government,
which is much more focused on mitigation than adaptation.
But planners have to additionally focus on adaptation.
And finally, there's an open question of what the role of land use
and built environment planning is.
We know there's lots of different ways that we can affect speed carbonization.
This is what this article argues.
I think said that that means planners have to reconceptualize our role
in planning cities and cities in the energy system.
So I hope you enjoy this lecture.
I hope you take this class or I hope you watch the subscript videos
on why cities are a key venue for future climate action.